Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is דף פ, Daf
Pe, בבא בתרא Bava Batra 80, and we pick up with the
משנה Mishna top of פ עמוד א. Pe Amud Aleph. הלוקח פירות
שובך מחברו, Halokeach Peirot Shovach Mechavero, somebody purchases the fruit, the offspring
of a dovecote from his friend, you're going to buy all the
baby doves.
מפריח בריכה ראשונה. Mafriach berecha rishona. So even though you are entitled
to all of the baby doves that are born from this, you
have to literally fly away, cause to fly away, but it really
means leave with the owner of the dovecote the first offspring,
the first... according to the רשב"ם Rashbam I don't know if this
is true, but apparently doves give birth once a month except one
month out of the year, and each time they give birth to
two, a male and a female. So that first brood, you have
to leave with the mother. And the reason is that if you
take away all of the babies, then the mother won't stay around
to have more kids, and the person who is selling you the
offspring still wants to keep the mother. Maybe you've bought the offspring
for the year, and then you know next year he wants there
to be more offspring and he wants maybe he doesn't want to
sell and he wants to keep it for himself. So you cannot
take every all of the doves and then the mother will fly
away, so you have to leave the first brood and that will
keep the mother there. Okay, so now as you can see we've
moved away from the earlier משניות Mishnayot which were all if you
buy A, do you buy all these other items that are come
sort of are associated with A? When you buy the house, do
you buy the well, when you buy the ship, do you buy
the cartons, etc.? Here clearly all of this is included, you are
buying the offspring but nevertheless it's understood that you leave something behind.
Okay, so that's in terms of the dovecote. פירות כוורת, Peirot kaveret,
if you buy the פירות Peirot and again this doesn't mean fruit
it means offspring of a beehive, you know you have a beehive
that's making honey and you want to start your own beehive business,
so you buy all of the all of the bees that are
born, then נוטל ג' נחילים ומסרס. Notel gimel nechilin umesares. You take
three נחילים nechilin swarms, apparently also again the bees give birth in
bunches and so and each bunch of births you can remove from
the hive and they are swarms and you'll start your own hive
with them. So you get the first three and afterwards you are
מסרס. mesares. Now we'll see in the גמרא Gemara the debate of
what מסרס mesares means, but for now let's assume it means you
sterilize... the owner rather has the right to sterilize the remaining bees.
The owner still wants to be producing honey and as long as
the bees are reproducing, they're not producing honey. Again I'm taking all
of this from the רשב"ם Rashbam I assume he knows what he's
talking about. So therefore after you have gotten the first three broods
and the first three swarms of baby bees, he is allowed to
sterilize the remaining you know the the the existing the current bees,
the old ones and get them back to producing honey. And we'll
see in the גמרא Gemara how he sterilizes them. Okay, חלות דבש,
Chalaot devash, מניח... maniach...
now let's say you're buying not the offspring but you're actually buying
the honey from the beehive, alright? So you are purchasing all of
the honey that comes from this beehive for this year, so מניח
שתי חלות. maniach shtei chalaot. You have to... it's understood that you
leave behind two of the loaves of honey, the you know the
honey mixed with the wax, because the bees are making honey because
that's their food. So this person is willing to sell you the
honey but he still wants to keep the beehive alive, you know
similar to the point, he's selling you certain things but he's not
trying to destroy his beehive, he's not trying to destroy his dovecote.
So the way you keep the beehive alive is you leave behind
two loaves and that will be the continued food for the remaining
bees and that you is not included in the honey that you
bought. זיתים ללקוט, מניח שתי גרופיות. Zeisim lilkot meniach shtei grufiyot.
And if you buy... and if somebody purchases olives and to cut
down and so the word ללקוט likkot to cut down means you're
not just plucking picking the olives off the tree, but you're actually
cutting off all of the branches with the olives. You still have
to leave behind two גרופיות, gurofiyot, branches, in order for the tree
to be able to grow back. Again you are getting the branches,
he is not trying to destroy his tree in the process. Alright,
let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. והתניא, Vatanya, בריכה ראשונה
ושניה? berecha rishona ushniya? The משנה Mishna says that when you buy
the offspring of the dovecote, you get the first... you leave behind
the first brood, but we have a ברייתא Baraita that says the
first and the second brood. So אמר רב כהנא לא קשיא, Amar
Rav Kahana lo kashya, הא לה הא לאימה. hala hali'ima. That's not
difficult, this is about her, this is about the mother. Now what
does this mean? So the רשב"ם Rashbam says there's a lot of...
it's a difficult גמרא Gemara and that there are a lot of
bad interpretations that he didn't like. He finally found one that more
or less works, so we're going to go with what and he...
so we're going to go with that explanation. And what he says
it means is that, okay, you left behind the first brood to
keep the mother there, to keep the dovecoat, you know, going, that's
fine. But then the that first brood, what's going to keep it
hanging around in the dovecoat? Right? It's going to grow up, and
then it's going to want to fly the coop, right? That's what
birds do. So the only way and if it flies the coop,
then the mother bird is not going to have its children there,
and it's going to want to fly the coop. So if you're
having the first dovecoat there to make sure the mother stays around
when that when that dovecoat, excuse me, that brood, if you're having
those two doves stay there to make sure that the mother stays
around, then you have to make sure that that brood stays there
when they grow up, when they grow up. So therefore it also
has to leave its first brood of that of that next generation
to keep that brood there. So הא לה הא לאימה Ha lah
ha leimah meaning that the משנה Mishna is talking about you leave
the first brood for the mother, but when you're also incorporating and
talking about the first brood itself, then you will say that it
that it also gets to have its first brood to stay behind.
So when it says you leave the first and the second, it
does not mean the first two broods of the mother. Okay, let's
call the generations A, B and C. A is the first generation,
the mother. Okay, and A gives birth to all of these babies
and you purchase the babies and you take home all the babies.
Okay, but B, which is the first of the birth of A,
that stays with the mom. Right now B is growing up. What's
going to keep it there? What's going to keep it there and
not fly the coop? And then the mom would fly is that
B gives birth to all these babies, but its first baby is,
and you get those too, because you bought all the offspring that
come from the new births from the coop. But the first babies
of B, C, they also stay in the coop. So or dovecoat.
So, and therefore when it says you leave behind the first and
second, it does not mean first two of A. It means the
first and second generations. Okay, so you leave behind B, first generation,
which is the first birth, the first brood from A, and you
leave behind when B grows up and has babies, you leave behind
C, the second generation. That's ראשונה ושנייה. Rishona u'shniya. Okay. So,
מאי שנא אמא דמצטטפה אברתא אזוגא דשבקינן לה. Mai shna ima demitztatfa
abarta azuga deshavkinan lah. So the גמרא Gemara says wait, I don't
understand why B needs to have C stay around in order to
keep it, you know, anchored in the coop. Because when you're dealing
with the mother, A, so then דמצטטפה demitztatfa it finds a, you
know, connection,
friendship, that's so with the, you know,
with אברתא abarta its daughter, ואזוגא ve'azuga and its mate. So the
mother is going to stay in the dovecoat because it's got its
daughter there and it's got its man there, its mate there,
דשבקינן לה deshavkinan lah that we leave it behind for the mother.
אי נמי Ee nami so B, why does B need to have
C around in order to stay anchored in the coop? אי נמי
תצטטף Ee nami titztatef
let it find, you know, like connection, anchoring, אמא ואזוגא דשבקינן לה.
Ima ve'azuga deshavkinan lah.
It's got its mom there, B has A, and B has its
husband. So if A can get by with its husband and its
child, why can't B get by with its husband and its mother?
Why do we have to leave B for, you know, its next
generation, C? So the גמרא Gemara says אמא אברתא מצטטפה אברתא אמא
לא מצטטפה. Ima abarta mitztatfa abarta ima lo mitztatfa. A mother, you
know, gets sort of anchoring, I'm
calling it, like a friendship, I'm looking for a better word here,
but it gets that through its, you know, attachment, it gets that
from its daughter. If its daughter is there, it's going to stay,
you know, in the dovecoat. But the daughter, what do kids do?
Kids grow up and they fly and they, you know, they fly
the coop.
So its daughter won't stay in the coop just because its mother
is there. That won't give it connection and anchoring. If you want
the daughter to stay in the coop, you have to have its
own child stay there and therefore for B you have to let
C stay there as well. And if C is there, then B
will be there, and if B is there, then A will stay
there. Okay. That was that. דתנו רבנן Detanu rabanan פירות כוורת נוטל
ג' נחילים ומסרס. Peiros kiveres notel gimel nechilum u'mesares.
When you're dealing with the bees from a hive and you've purchased
the newly born bees, so you get the first three swarms and
then you are מסרס mesares then the way we're reading it is
the owner has the right now to sterilize the... the remaining bees
so that they will make honey. במה Bameh מסרסן? mesaresan? Now how
do you sterilize them? Okay. So אמר Amar רב Rav יהודה Yehuda
אמר Amar שמואל Shmuel בחרדל, bechardal, you have them
eat mustard and that will have some effect that it'll sterilize them
and get them back to making honey. אמרי Amri במערבא bamaarava they
said in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisroel משמיה דרבי יוסי ברבי חנינא mishmei
deRabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina לא lo חרדל chardal מסרסן, mesarsan, it's
not really that the mustard makes sterilizes them when they eat mustard,
אלא ella מתוך mitokh שפיהן shepihen חד chad but they eat the
mustard and their mouth is very sharp, they have the sharp taste
of mustard. So what do you do if you're at a meal
and you have something that's has a very sharp taste? You look
for something sweet to eat. So therefore ואכלו veokhlo את es דובשן,
dovshan, then they go and they eat their honey and they're spending
time, you know, and once apparently the thinking here is the way
the רשב"ם Rashbam understands it, if they're spending time eating honey then
they're not spending time having sex
and having babies, and also presumably if they're eating honey they're also
producing honey. All right, so however the mechanics worked, you got them
to be sterilized and now they're producing honey and he is allowed
to do that the owner once you've had the first three swarms.
רבי יוחנן אמר Rabbi Yochanan amar נוטל notel שלשה shlosha נחילים nechilim
בסירוס. besirus. He says you misunderstood the word ומסרסן. umesarsam. It does
not mean ומסרס—excuse umesares me, it does not mean from the word
סירוס, sirus, you know, it does not mean that you sterilize them,
it means
like from the word also סירוגין, serugin, which is not knitted כיפות,
kippos, but it means that you alternate. So he says what it
means is is that you get three swarms in alternation. Alright שלשה
shlosha נחילים nechilim בסירוס. besirus. במתניתא—so Bematnisa that means that you get,
you know, swarm one, then swarm three, and then swarm five and
the owner gets two and four and six. Because the earlier ones
presumably are of stronger and better quality. So rather than you the
purchaser getting all three
good strong first three swarms, you alternate and you get one, three,
and five and the owner gets the other ones. That's how he
reads it. בסירוס. besirus. Okay. במתניתא תנא, Bematnisa tena, in the ברייתא
Braisa we taught נוטל notel ג' gimmel נחילים nechilim זה ze אחר
achar זה. ze. No, you get the first three, one, two, and
three, you purchased the baby bees, you get all three of the
first three swarms. מכאן ואילך, Mikan ve'eilach, so and from that point
on, נוטל notel אחת achas ומניח umaniach אחת. achas. You alternate. So
yes, the word סירוס sirus does mean alternate, which is a much
better read of the משנה, Mishnah, but it does not mean three
in alternation, right? It means three and then you start alternating and
that is the much better read of the
משנה. Mishnah. נוטל notel ג' gimmel נחילים nechilim ומסרס umesares and from
that point on you do alternate swarms. Okay. חלות Chalos
דבש devash מניח maniakh שתי shtei חלות. chalos. Now if you're getting
the honey you have to leave behind two loaves of honey for
the bees to eat from.
אמר Amar רב כהנא Rav Kahana דבש devash בכוורת, bekiveres, if you
have honey that is still in the beehive, it's still mixed with
wax and let's even assume it's in the hive itself, so אינו
eino יוצא yotzei מידי midei מאכל maakhal לעולם. leolam. It never loses
its status of food. Now this means two things.
Number one it means that it automatically is considered food even before
you have removed it from the hive and taken out the wax.
That's a little bit of a surprise, you know, because it's like
it's not yet normally in the state that people are ready to
eat it. But okay, that's what he's saying here. He's saying you
cannot make it something other than food. It has that status and
maybe it has that status automatically.
The other thing he is saying is that it is not liquid
but it is solid, it is food, and therefore טומאה tumah purposes,
there's a difference between whether you consider something to be a liquid
or a solid. Now תוספות Tosafos actually points out that הלכתית halakhically
דבש, devash, honey is one of the seven liquids, but תוספות Tosafos
says that that's when it is removed from the wax. But when
it is in the beehive he says it is food, it starts
off as food, it's nothing other than food, and it will be
can be nothing else than food in that inside the beehive in
its wax state. It cannot be considered liquid. Okay, so that's his
ruling. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara does with this.
מתיבי, Mesvei, the גמרא Gemara says I'll challenge that. I'm sorry, skipped
a line. אלמא Alma says the גמרא Gemara קסבר kasavar לא lo
בעי baei מחשבה. machshava.
So that means that you're saying that you don't need to have
intent to eat it in order to make it food. And it
is automatically considered to be food because that's what you're going to
do with it, you're going to eat the honey. It's standing there,
you know, the same way you don't have to think that an
apple is food for it הלכתית halakhically to have that you're planning
on eating an apple. An apple is automatically considered הלכתית halakhically food
and it gets טומאה tumah of foodstuffs and makes other things טמא
tamei and it's
all. planning to remove the honey in order to eat it. So
the גמרא Gemara says, אמר לו לא בעי מחשבה, Amar lo lo
bayei machshava, so you're telling me so that it does not need
intent to remove it and to plan to eat it to give
it the status of food. So מיתיבי, meitvei, I'll challenge you on
this: דבש בכוורת אינו לא אוכל ולא משקה. devash bekiveret eino lo
ochel velo mashkeh. We have a ברייתא Braita that teaches that when
it's still in the beehive and when it's still in the wax,
it does not yet have the status
of food or liquid. It is not like an apple, all right,
you know, because and as we can sort of intuit, maybe you're
going to leave it there in order for the bees to eat
from it and it's not going to be human food. So how
do you reconcile these teachings? One is that it's just like an
apple, it doesn't need any special intent, it automatically is food, and
that's
רב פפא's Rav Pappa statement, excuse me, רב כהנא's Rav Kahana statement,
and then this ברייתא Braita that says that it is while it's
still in the beehive, it is not considered food. So אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, says אביי, Abaye,
or liquid. לא צריכא אלא לאותן שתי חלות. Lo tzricha ella le-otan
shtei chalot.
That ברייתא Braita is talking about the two loaves that are left
behind for the bees. That makes a lot of sense, okay, if
the basic industry of beehives is you take out all of the
honey and you leave behind two loaves, so all of the normal
honey is, that's why it's being raised, you know, it's there in
order to be eaten, you know, and and it's considered, it doesn't
need any special intent and it's considered to be food, whereas the
things that are left specifically for the bees and to maintain the
beehive, that does not have a status of food unless you specifically
intend to remove it and to eat it. Okay, that's very reasonable.
רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava says, רבי אליעזר היא. Rabbi Eliezer
hi. No, this ברייתא Braita that says it is not considered food,
the honey in the beehive, is going like רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer.
What רבי אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer? דתנן, ditnan, top of פ"ג עמוד ב'
Pe-Gimmel Amud Bet and we had this משנה Mishna earlier:
כוורת דבורים, Kiveret devorim, if you've got a beehive, and תוספות Tosafot
says that we're talking about here about the hive but the honey
in the hive, okay, that really is the only way to read
this in this גמרא Gemara and in general, רבי אליעזר אומר הרי
היא כקרקע. Rabbi Eliezer omer harei hi ke-karka. I treat the honey
in a hive just like I would treat an apple still attached
to a tree, that it's considered to be part of the land,
it's still attached to the tree, so it is like land. וכותבין
עליה פרוזבול, ve-kotvin aleha pruzbul, you can write a פרוזבול pruzbul in
order for שמיטה Shemita not to annul the debt, which can only
be written if the debtor has land. ואינה מקבלת טומאה במקומה, ve-eina
mekabeles tumah bimkomah, and as long as the honey is there in
the hive, it's like an apple attached to the tree. I was
giving the example an apple's food, but it cannot become טמא tamei
until it's removed from the tree, the apple. And here too because
it's still considered part of the land. So here too the honey
in the hive, it's not like, you know, you could say it
doesn't grow in the hive, it's placed in the hives and manufactured
in the hive by the bees, so you could say the honey
in the hive is just like, you know, like you had a
basket hanging from your tree and you put apples in it. Yes,
that wouldn't be considered קרקע, karka, but רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer חידוש
chiddush is no, I consider it to be like the same way
the apple grew from the tree, I consider this to be sort
of like a product from the hive, he's not saying that's how
it was made, but it's still attached to the hive and attached
to the ground and it's like the ground, and therefore it cannot
yet become טמא. tamei. והרודה ממנה בשבת חייב חטאת, ve-ha-rodeh mimena be-shabbat
chayav chatat, and here perhaps is the most surprising ruling. If you
take the honey out of the hive on שבת, Shabbat, you have
transgressed, you are חייב, chayav, you did a מלאכה. melacha. Now, if
I had apples in that hive or apples hanging from a basket
in a tree, I would not be חייב chayav on שבת. Shabbat.
You're only חייב chayav on שבת Shabbat when you pluck something, קוצר,
kotzer, from where it is growing. But he says I get that
the bees make the honey, but still הלכתית halachically we look at
it as if it's growing from the ground, and if you take
it off of the tree it's like you picked an apple from
a tree and you are חייב חטאת, chayav chatat, you have violated
שבת. Shabbat. So, if
the... well let's just finish this and then we'll explain what this
has to do with the question about אוכל ochel or משקה. mashkeh.
אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Elazar, says רבי אלעזר Rabbi Elazar the
אמורא, Amora, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? mai ta'ama de-Rabbi Eliezer? דכתיב ויטבול
אותה ביערות דבש, dichtiv vayitbol otah be-yaarot devash,
and he dipped it in the יערות דבש, yaarot devash, the literally
like the forest of honey. וכי מה עניין יער אצל דבש? ve-chi
ma inyan yaar etzel devash?
Why is it using the word יער yaar which means a forest
in the context of honey? אלא לומר לך מה יער התולש ממנו
בשבת חייב חטאת, ella lomar lecha ma yaar ha-toleish mimenu be-shabbat chayav
chatat, to tell you the same way by a forest, by if
you pick an apple from a tree that's considered picking something from
where it grows and you're חייב chayav on שבת, Shabbat, אף דבש
הרודה ממנו בשבת חייב חטאת, af devash ha-rodeh mimenu be-shabbat chayav chatat,
the same about honey. And the הלכה halacha is going to look
at it as if it grew in the hive and grew from
the ground and it's like קרקע karka and for all of these
הלכות. halachot. So why is that relevant for us? It's relevant for
us because if it is like an apple still attached to a
tree, then... It cannot, it's not food and it's not liquid. It
doesn't matter what you're planning on doing with it or not planning
on doing with it. As long as it's still there and it's
still attached to the ground, it cannot become טמא. tamei. So the
ברייתא Braita that said that honey is neither a solid or a
liquid when it's in the hive is רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that
does not consider it to be like in a basket. He considers
it to be attached to the ground. And therefore it is not
food or liquid because it's still quote-unquote growing from the ground until
it's picked, until it's taken down, it will not be able to
become טמא. tamei. Okay, two very interesting different interpretations. Both of them,
you know, make good sense. So now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara does with this. מיתיבי, Meisvei, I will challenge you. דבש שזב
מכוורתו אינו לא אוכל ולא משקה. Dvash she-zav mi-kavarto aino lo ochel
ve-lo mashke. If honey flows from the hive, actually the honey is,
you know, removed from the hive, maybe even liquified and separated from
the wax, okay, so the ברייתא Braita teaches it is neither food
nor liquid. Now that's pretty strange. It's removed from the wax, it's
removed from the hive and it's neither food nor liquid? So how
does that make sense? So the גמרא Gemara says,
we have to finish, if you intended לאכילה le-achila to eat this
honey, then מטמא טומאת אוכלין. metamei tumas ochlin. Then it has the
laws of טומאה, tumah, it can become טמא, tamei, it's considered food
and it goes by, you know, those laws. What the amount, minimum
amount is, כביצה, k'beitza, the size of an egg and so on,
in order for it to become, for it to become טמא tamei
or to pass on the
טומאה, tumah, becoming טמא tamei might be even a small amount. למשקין,
le-mashkin, מטמא טומאת משקין. metamei tumas mashkin.
If
however you plan on treating this as a liquid, you know, are
you going to, how are you going to do it? Are you
going to sort of like do it as something dripping on something
and treat it as a liquid, you know, and you'll sort of,
or drink it for all I know, maybe make it into mead,
then it has the status of liquids and that goes by a
different שיעור, shiur, that goes by the שיעור shiur of a רביעית.
revi'is. So here what this ברייתא Braita is saying is when the
honey comes from the hive it still has no status of food
or liquid, only once you, even if it's now no longer in
the hive and it's removed from the wax, only once you decide
to eat it will it have that halachic status of food or
liquid depending on whether you decide to eat it or decide to
drink it. So how does this make sense according to the various
interpretations? So it certainly does not fit with רב פפא, Rav Pappa,
who keep, I keep on saying רב פפא Rav Pappa again, it
was who was it, it was רב כהנא Rav Kahana who said
that it is, well let's, that it is automatically food. This says
that it starts off as neither food nor liquid. So let's see
how it can work according to both of the interpretations. בשלמא לאביי
ניחא. Bishlama le-Abaye niha.
For אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye said רב כהנא Rav Kahana says normal
honey in the hive is automatically food. But the ברייתא Braita said
it's neither food nor liquid when it was talking about the two
loaves left for the bees. So this works perfectly. This is talking
about the two loaves left for the bees, that's neither food nor
liquid. Even when it gets separated from the wax, it doesn't yet
have the status of food because it started its life without that
status until you intend to use it as food. Okay, so for
אביי Abaye you have normal honey in a hive, it's not growing
from the ground, it's, the default is it's going to be eaten,
so therefore it has the status of food. But you have the
two loaves left for the bees, the default is it's not going
to be eaten, that doesn't have a status of food or liquid.
When it gets, those two loaves, the honey gets separated from the
wax, okay, it's still nothing because it started its life as not
food, so it's still nothing, but it can become food or liquid
when you intend to eat it or drink it. So everything works
as a very nice package according to אביי. Abaye. However, אלא לרבא
קשיא. ella le-Rava kashya. For רבא Rava it's a difficulty. Because for
רבא, Rava, right, the thing that would start off its life as
neither food nor liquid would be according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
that it's considered attached to the ground. So if that's the idea
that it's considered to be attached to the ground, then as soon
as it's no longer attached to the ground, as soon as it
is flowing and separated, then it should revert to the normal status
of honey, which is that honey is food. So why do you
need special מחשבה? machshava? That is the question. אלא לרבא קשיא. ella
le-Rava kashya. אמר רב זביד כגון שזב אגב כלי מאוס. Amar Rav
Zevid k'gon she-zav agav kli ma'us. No,
we're talking about that when it flowed, it flowed on a, over
a or into a disgusting vessel. רב אחא בר יעקב אמר כגון
שזב אגב קסקסין. Rav Acha bar Yaakov amar k'gon she-zav agav kaskasin.
It flowed over like wood chips. basically got absorbed and there's no
way you can sort of hold onto it. So what does this
mean? It means the following: that if something starts as food, let's
say according to אביי, Abaye, you know, normal honey starts as food,
according to אביי Abaye's read, right? That everybody sort of agrees that,
if it's not the two loaves, then once something starts as food,
just because it goes into a disgusting vessel or into the onto
the wood chips, as long as it's still edible by a dog,
halakhically it's still food for טומאה tumah purposes. Okay. So according so
if we were going like the רבנן, Rabbanan, the fact that it
would go into a, you know, into a type of a vessel,
a disgusting vessel wouldn't change. But now let's talk about רבא Rava
and רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. According to רבא Rava and רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, this stuff started off as not food because it was
attached to the ground.
So that's the ברייתא braita that says it's neither food nor liquid.
Now, if it
it should be that as soon as it gets detached from the
ground and flows, it automatically is food. Why does the ברייתא braita
require that you have מחשבה? machshava? Because when it started flowing, it
flowed onto this disgusting vessel and which is not which would make
it not normally edible by humans. So since it it would normally
not be edible by humans, it still does not automatically get the
status of food and you need specifically to have intent to eat
it in order to give it that status. Okay, so that's where
we are. To repeat, this might be, you know, a little complicated,
but according to אביי, Abaye,
according to רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, normal honey food, even when it's
in the hive. Two loaves, not food, planned for the bees. If
those two loaves start the the honey starts, you know, flowing and
it gets removed from the the the wax, then still not food
because it was set aside for the bees. But if you have
specific מחשבה, machshava, that will turn it into food or liquid. Okay,
that's אביי. Abaye. רבא, Rava,
according to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, according to רב כהנא Rav Kahana
who's not רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, the honey in the hive is
automatically food. According to רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, it's like an apple
growing from a tree, so it's nothing, it's attached to the ground.
As soon as it starts flowing, in a normal case, it's no
longer attached to the ground, it should automatically be food. But if
it starts flowing on top of a disgust or into a disgusting
vessel, because it's not edible by nor because it would not normally
be eaten by humans, it still does not have a status on
food unless you have specific מחשבה machshava to eat it or to
drink it. All right, almost at the end of this discussion.
Okay.
Now מתיבי, Maitibi, I'll challenge you. דבש בכוורת אינו לא אוכל ולא
משקה. Devash be-kiverta eino lo ochel v'lo mashkeh. We have another ברייתא.
braita. Honey in the hive is neither food nor liquid. So again,
that sounds like the the teaching that was against רב כהנא Rav
Kahana and this is going to be the debate of אביי Abaye
and רבא, Rava, what the context is. חישב עליו לאכילה מטמא טומאת
אוכלים למשקה מטמא טומאת משקה. Chishav alav l'achila metameh tumat ochlim l'mashkeh
metameh tumat mashkeh. If you think to eat it, it becomes food
for טומאה tumah purposes, and if you plan on drinking it, it
becomes liquid for טומאה tumah purposes.
So בשלמא לאביי ניחא, Bishlama l'Abaye nicha, according to אביי, Abaye, it's
great. It's the two loaves that are left for the bees. They
are neither food nor drink because they're left for the bees. But
if you plan on removing it for human consumption, then it will
be food or liquid depending on how you're going to treat it.
אלא לרבא קשיא, Ela l'Rava kashya, but for רבא, Rava, we have
we're back to our problem. Because this only makes sense according to
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer that says it's neither food nor drink because
it's considered connected to the ground. Well, once it's connected to the
ground, your מחשבה machshava doesn't matter. You can't your מחשבה machshava to
eat an apple doesn't make it able to become טמא tameh as
long as it's connected to the ground. So since for רבא Rava
the beginning of the ברייתא braita that says it's neither food nor
drink only works according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer because it's and
who says it's like it's connected to the ground, what do you
do with the end that says your מחשבה machshava makes it considered
food? So אמר לך רבא, Amar lach Rava, רבא Rava would say
to you, תרץ הכי, taretz hachi, here's how you have to read
it. חישב עליו לאכילה אינו מטמא טומאת אוכלים למשקה אינו מטמא טומאת
משקה. Chishav alav l'achila eino metameh tumat ochlim l'mashkeh eino metameh tumat
mashkeh. Just add the word אינו. eino. If you thought, if you
plan to eat it or to drink it, it does not become
טמא tameh and that's what the ברייתא braita is saying. Okay, so
it does not say it can become טמא, tameh, it is saying
it cannot become טמא. tameh. תניא כוותיה דרב כהנא, Tanya kevata de-Rav
Kahana, we taught like רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. דבש בכוורת מטמא טומאת
אוכלים שלא במחשבה. Devash be-kiverta metameh tumat ochlim she-lo be-machshava. We taught
like רב כהנא, Rav Kahana, honey even when it's in the hive
is automatically considered food and you do not need any מחשבה machshava
to give it that status. Okay, so in the end, everybody seems
to agree to the position of רב כהנא. Rav Kahana. אביי Abaye
says it would be different by the two loaves that are left
behind since that's not planned for human consumption, it's planned specifically for
bee consumption, that is not considered food unless you specifically have that
מחשבה. machshava. And רבא. Rava. Rava would say according to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer, the honey would be considered something growing from the ground
and would not be considered food and even מחשבה machshava would not
work until it actually got separated from the hive. Okay, moving on.
Last case in the משנה. Mishna.
זיתים ללקוט Zeitim likkot, מניח שתי גרופיות. maniach shtei gurofiyot. If you're
buying olive trees to cut down the branches, you still have to
leave two branches. תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: הלוקח אילן מחבירו ללקוט מגביה
מן הקרקע טפח וקוצץ. Halokeach ilan michaveiro lilkot magbi'ah min hakarka tefach
vekotzetz. If somebody bought a tree from his friend to cut it
down, you have to first start cutting it down a טפח tefach
off the ground, like three or four inches off the ground, in
order to allow the tree to grow back after you cut it
down because you only bought the wood of the tree, not the
right to uproot it.
בבתולת השקמה, Bevisulas hashikmah, if you are buying a virgin sycamore tree,
something that's never been cut, ג' טפחים. gimmel tefachim. You have to
leave three טפחים tefachim close to the ground and then it'll grow
back.
סדן השקמה, Sdan hashikmah, if you are buying a sycamore tree that's
already been cut down once and grow back, then ב' טפחים, beis
tefachim, it's sufficient to leave two טפחים tefachim near the ground, it's
a stronger tree, whatever, and it will grow back even with just
two טפחים tefachim left near the ground. בקנים ובגפנים, Bekanim uvegfanim, if
you are buying reeds or grapevines
to cut them, so מן הפקק ולמעלה, min hapkak ulema'alah, you have
to cut above the knot in the vine or in the reed.
בדקלים ובארזים, Bidekalim uve'arazim, if it is in date palms or cedar
trees, you're buying them in order to cut them down,
חופר ומשריש, chofer umesharesh, then you can actually uproot them and dig
into the dirt and uproot them because those are trees that once
cut will never grow back and therefore if you're buying to cut
it you do not have to leave anything for to grow because
it won't grow back. שאין גזעו מחליף, she'ein gizmo machalif, because their
trunk does not grow back.
So that's the ברייתא. Baraisa. So now let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. בבתולת השקמה ג' טפחים בעינן? Bevisulas hashikmah gimmel tefachim be'inan?
Do you really need three טפחים tefachim for a virgin sycamore? ורמינהי,
Vermini, I'll challenge you: אין קוצצין בבתולת השקמה בשביעית מפני שהיא עבודה.
Ein kotzetzin bevisulas hashikmah beshevi'is mipnei shehi avodah. You're not allowed to
cut down a virgin sycamore on שביעית Shevi'is because it is causing
it to grow, it is literally an עבודה, avodah, one of the
prohibited acts on שביעית. Shevi'is. Meaning you're allowed to pick apples off
of a tree on שביעית, Shevi'is, but you're not allowed to prune
a tree in order that it grows. That's שדך לא תזרע וכרמך
לא תזמור sadcha lo tizra vecharmecha lo tizmor which gets understood by
the Rabbis you can't do anything that's going to cause the crops
or whatever to be growing or the trees or anything
to be enhancing their growth. So if so it says, so what
does the ברייתא Baraisa say? So
you can't cut it at all it sounds like because you cut
it it's going to cause it grow. Okay, so far that's consistent
with what we've been teaching that when you cut it
down a new one grows in its place. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
אומר: omer: כדרכו אסור. kidarko asur. If you would do it normally,
the way the sycamores are cut that allow then a new one
to grow up, then it is forbidden because then you're encouraging growth.
אלא, Ella, but here's the way it would be permissible to do
it if you really just wanted the wood, you wanted it to
be like picking an apple, you just wanted the wood of the
sycamore tree. So here's what you are allowed to do. מגביה י'
טפחים וקוצץ, Magbi'ah yud tefachim vekotzetz, either start cutting higher than ten
טפחים tefachim because then it really won't grow back and then you're
just getting it for the wood, או גומם מעם הארץ, o gomem
me'im ha'aretz, not מעם הארץ, me'am ha'aretz, וגומם מעם הארץ, ugomem me'im
ha'aretz,
or you level it and you cut it right against the ground.
Alright, so in those two scenarios it will not be encouraging the
growth, it'll just be getting the wood and that will be permissible
on שביעית. Shevi'is. So what do we see from this? We see
that it seems like the only way you stop it from growing
back is cutting it totally straight against the ground. So why did
we need to leave three טפחים tefachim in order for it to
grow back? So that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to ask.
מעם הארץ הוא דקשי, Me'im ha'aretz hu dekashei, oh only when you
cut it against the ground is it going to be bad for
the tree and it won't grow back, האידך מעלי ליה, ha'idach ma'ali
lei, if you leave even a little near the ground it'll grow
back, so why do you have to leave three טפחים tefachim near
the ground? אמר אביי: Amar Abaye: ג' טפחים מעלי ליה. gimmel tefachim
ma'ali lei. There's like a range. Three טפחים, tefachim, when you cut
it three טפחים, tefachim, that's going to be really good and it'll
grow back as it should and that'll be encouraging growth. מעם הארץ,
Me'im ha'aretz, if you cut it totally flat against the ground, ודאי
קשי ליה, vadai kashi lei, that is certainly going to be bad
for the tree and it won't grow back at all. מכאן ואילך,
mikan ve'eilach, but what in that space between zero and three? In
that middle space, so מכאן mikan ואילך, vaeilakh, לא מקשי קשי ליה,
lo makshe kashi lei, it's not bad for it, ולא מעלי מעלי
ליה, velo ma'ale ma'ali lei, it's not great for it either. Okay,
so it'll grow back but not as well. as well as it
should. Let's say that's what he means. גבי שביעית עבדינן מידי דודאי
קשי ליה. gabei shvi'is avdinan midi d'vadi kashi lei. By שמיטה, Shmita,
we want to allow you to cut it and to use the
wood, if that's what we want to allow. We have to make
sure that what you're doing is not considered in any way encouraging
growth. So we want you to cut it straight against the ground
because if you leave even a little bit, it will encourage growth.
Not great growth, but it'll encourage growth. גבי מקח וממכר עבדינן מידי
דודאי מעלי ליה. gabei mekach umimkar avdinan midi d'vadi ma'ali lei.
But when it comes to purchasing and you're buying this tree for
the wood from your friend, then you have to make sure that
you are leaving him behind something decent. And therefore you're going to
cut it from three טפחים tfachim so he has something nice to
grow back.
Okay, fine. Now, moving on. So that's why it says three טפחים,
tfachim, because you want something nice to grow back. You could cut
lower and it will grow back, and that'll be a שמיטה Shmita
problem, but it won't be so nice. בדקלים ובארזים חופר ומשריש, bidkalim
uva'arazim chofer umashreish, when it comes to palm trees and cedar trees,
you can uproot the whole thing לפי שאין גזעו מחליף lfi she'ein
giz'o machalif because it will not grow back if you cut it.
So the גמרא Gemara says, וארז אין גזעו מחליף? ve'erez ein giz'o
machalif? Is it true that a cedar tree it won't grow back
if you cut it? והא דרש רבי חייא בר לולינא? veha darash
Rabbi Chiya bar Lulina? But didn't Rabbi Chiya bar Lulina explicate: מאי
דכתיב, mai d'ichtiv, what is meant by the verse, צדיק כתמר יפרח
כארז בלבנון ישגה, tzadik katamar yifrach ke'erez balvanon yisgeh,
that the righteous person will like a palm tree will blossom forth,
and like a cedar of the Lebanon will increase? So what does
that mean? ישגה. yisgeh. אם נאמר תמר למה נאמר ארז ואם נאמר
ארז למה נאמר תמר? im ne'emar tamar lamah ne'emar erez ve'im ne'emar
erez lamah ne'emar tamar?
Why did it have to compare a righteous person to both a
cedar and a palm tree? If it said palm, why did it
have to say cedar? And if it said cedar, why did it
have to say palm? So the גמרא Gemara says, אילו נאמר ארז
ולא נאמר תמר, ilu ne'emar erez velo ne'emar tamar, הייתי אומר מה
ארז אינו עושה פירות אף צדיק אינו עושה פירות. hayisi omer mah
erez eino oseh peiros af tzadik eino oseh peiros.
How are you comparing a צדיק tzadik to a cedar?
A cedar doesn't bear fruit. So are you trying to tell me
that a צדיק tzadik won't bear fruit? His good acts, let's say
we mean it in that way, you know, won't bear him reward
in this world or in the next world? That's not a good
metaphor. לכך נאמר תמר. lekach ne'emar tamar. So therefore it wanted to
compare the צדיק tzadik to a palm tree so that you have
the image that the righteous person's actions do bear fruit. ואם נאמר
תמר ולא נאמר ארז, ve'im ne'emar tamar velo ne'emar erez, הייתי אומר
מה תמר אין גזעו מחליף אף צדיק אין גזעו מחליף. hayisi omer
mah tamar ein giz'o machalif af tzadik ein giz'o machalif.
I would have said, but wait a minute,
a palm tree when you cut it down, it doesn't grow back.
So are you coming to tell me that a righteous person, let's
say if he stumbles and falls, I don't mean literally, spiritually or
in other ways, that he won't be able to, you know, pick
himself up again? Is that supposed to be the image and the
message? That's what I would have thought if you only compared him
to a palm tree. לכך נאמר ארז. lekach ne'emar erez. Therefore it
also compared him to a cedar tree so you should know that
even if a צדיק tzadik stumbles, he will eventually, you know, rise
up again. So what do you see? You see here that cedar
trees do grow back. It's very funny that it's bringing a proof,
you know, not just from a, hey let's go look outdoors and
see what happens when this actually happens, but okay, you know, it's
an easier way to cite a source if you're in the בית
מדרש beis medrash to cite a textual source. So it's clear from
this textual source that cedar trees do grow back. So what does
the other ברייתא braisa mean that cedar trees do not grow back?
So let's see what the גמרא's Gemara answer. אלא הכא במאי עסקינן
בשאר מיני ארזים. ela hacha bemai askinan bish'ar minei arazim. We're talking
here when it says that cedar trees don't grow back, by other
things that are called ארז erez but that are not cedar trees.
Other types of cedars. Those are the ones that don't grow back.
כדרבה בר רב הונא. kiderabba bar rav huna. Like Rabba bar Rav
Huna. דאמר רבה בר רב הונא אמרי בי רב, de'amar Rabba bar
Rav Huna amri bei rav, עשרה מיני ארזים הם. asarah minei arazim
hem.
There are ten types of cedar or ten things that are called
ארז. erez. All right? שנאמר, shene'emar, as the verse says, אתן במדבר
ארז. eten bamidbar erez. I will give in the wilderness an ארז.
erez. And then it lists different species: שיטה והדס ועץ שמן, shita
vehadas ve'etz shemen, אשים asim etc.
So now the גמרא Gemara is going to go through all of
these and tell you what they are. ארז ארזא. erez arza. So
ארז erez means, okay, cedar. Okay. שיטה תורניתא. shita turnisa. The next
word in the פסוק, pasuk, תורניתא. turnisa. So that means the acacia
tree.
הדס אסא. hadas asa. הדס hadas means the myrtle.
עץ שמן אפרסמא. etz shemen afarsma. So what is עץ שמן? etz
shemen? That's אפרסמא, afarsma, which the Koren says means a pine tree.
All right. ברות ברתי. berosh barti. Then it goes on, אשים ברות,
asim berosh, I will give ברות. berosh. What's ברות? berosh? ברתי. barti.
So
ברות berosh is juniper.
Excuse me, I take that back. The Koren says that עץ שמן
etz shemen actually means the balsam tree. I know, so I guess
that's different than the palm tree. Anyway, ברוש brosh is juniper. תדהר,
tidhar, what is תדהר? tidhar? So that is שאגא shaga again. שאגא
shaga which again at least the Koren says means teak. ותאשור ute'ashur
and what's תאשור? te'ashur? שורבינא shurbina which is cypress. So most of
these I'm getting again from the Koren. Okay, so anyway,
those are the things that are called ארז. erez. So there are
ten types of ארז. erez. So all of those that aren't cedar
are the ones that will not grow back. But the גמרא gemara
is not done because you said there were ten, but this פסוק
pasuk only lists seven. So the גמרא gemara says הני שבעה הוו,
hani shiva havei, those are only seven. So כי אתא רב דימי
אמר הוסיפו עליהם, ki ata Rav Dimi amar hosifu aleihem, when Rav
Dimi came, no, so the verse only mentioned seven, but later Rabbis
explained that there were three other things that are also called ארז,
erez, and what are they? אלונים, alonim, אלמונים, almonim, and אלמוגים. almugim.
Those three trees. What are they? אלונים alonim is בוטני. butni. So
אלונים alonim is pistachio trees. אלמונים, almonim, בלוטי. baluti. Those are oaks.
And אלמוגים, almugim, what are אלמוגים? almugim? כסיתא. kasita. Those are coral
trees. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri, others say not אלונים, alonim, אלמונים almonim
whatever, but ארונים, aronim, ערמונים, armonim, אלמוגים. almugim. And what are those?
ארונים aronim is ערי, arei, laurel trees. ערמונים armonim is דולבי, dulvi,
plane trees. And אלמוגים, almugim, כסיתא, kasita, those are coral trees. All
right, so I have no idea what these are, I don't know
whether they are or are not a variation of cedar, I have
a feeling that a lot of those are not variations of cedar,
but anyway the point being that one ברייתא baraita says ארז erez
grows back and one says it does not, and the גמרא gemara
says it depends what type of ארז erez you are talking about.
Okay, we will end here.